welcome to the stoa
the stoa is a digital campfire where we
cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the knife's edge
of what's happening now
all right let's begin check-ins
um yeah i'm feeling a giddiness
that's the word that's lining right now
giddiness
so welcome to the stoa i'm peter limberg
the steward of the stoa and it still has
a place for us to go here and dialogue
about what matters most
at the knife's edge of this moment and
uh today i am
probably giddy for a reason because the
the boys
from platinum magazine are here um we
have
wolf tivi uh co-founder and
editor-in-chief uh
taivee i was good i should have asked
how to pronounce it wolf
type all right everyone gets it so write
a passage in order to uh
uh have affiliate with you my friend
okay so uh co-founder and
editor-in-chief and then ash
milton uh managing editor hi everyone
so how uh yeah i think platinum came on
my radar is um
i don't know somebody tweeted at me and
ash and then we got coffee and i'm like
how about so much freaking cool people
in toronto and then i started like
reading uh played a magazine and then
started seeing that they're similar
players that are associated with like
our friend samuel berger who does um
live players here at the stoa and so for
those of you who do not know
plato magazines their mission is summed
up as governance
futurism uh and it's a non-partisan
publication that explores the future of
liberalism governance and society
through responsible
slow publishing uh political theory and
investigative journalism
so what we're gonna do today is wolf and
ash
are going to kind of share their
thoughts
on the magazine and then the topic at
hand and then we're going to pivot to a
q a
and if you have a question anytime it
comes to you right in the chat box
and when the q a portion begins i will
call on you i'll mute yourself
ask your question if you want me to read
on your behalf indicate that in the chat
box
so that being said i'm going to taken
wolf
cool thanks a lot peter all right i see
a lot of familiar faces in the audience
that's good
i know some of you for those i haven't
met nice to meet you
yeah so let's talk about palladium so
the basic thesis of palladium
is that america is in rough shape
politically and ideologically and
intellectually
and we conceived of the project
as a way to start changing that as a way
to create
a little corner in the discourse where
it is possible to discuss
things frankly and at a high level of
quality
so that we can
create a community of people who
[Music]
can hopefully help contribute as
we get through the next couple decades
of
trouble uh so the basic kind of
historical thesis is we're reaching the
end
of kind of a period of
stability complacency um
and and we're entering into kind of a
period of perhaps
more chaos and decay and this is a
natural cycle within any complex system
you have things built up and then they
decay
and the way uh that we have to approach
these things as historical actors
is that we have to find
ways to detach from the stuff that is
broken
and build new things that isn't going to
be dragged down so if you think of it in
terms of winter and spring
in the winter in the fall there is
generally a bunch of things decaying but
there are also
seeds being sown and then in the spring
things come back
up so that's kind of a very metaphorical
way to describe what we're doing we're
trying to sow the seeds of new growth
in civilization and social technology
and particular america's institutions
early in this period of what we expect
to be
a lot of change so what we do to
accomplish that
is we publish as peter was saying we
publish long form
we publish analysis of things that are
going on in the world we publish
analysis of things that are going on in
america
we're trying to kind of take a
philosophical long-term
relatively realist approach
to what's going on in the world
and we summarize this as we're trying to
produce navigation grade information
for the people who are going to be
future institution buildings
um so you know you need to look at the
world you need to understand what's
going on well enough to actually
navigate it
and a lot of the kind of currently
existing media
the mainstream doesn't necessarily
always provide that for you a lot of
time it's narrative
it's trying to suck you into a political
thing um
it's operating within established
paradigms which are what actually is
failing so we're trying to get out of
established paradigms
look at things with fresh eyes so that's
the first aspect the second aspect
is we're trying to provide fresh visions
new visions for
what kind of people we should be what
kind of society we should be building
in particular visions for a sort of
prospective elite
if we're thinking about who's actually
making decisions in society it's the
people with
most power so we try to approach these
questions from the first person so to
speak of like well what would
what should an elite be interested in um
and so we try to build visions for
where we should be taking society from
from that perspective of how do you
govern a society well and responsibly
and so this um this produces kind of the
concept of governance futurism
and then additionally we have a third
pillar of the project which
is the community we think that
one of the most important and high
leverage ways to impact history and
and impact the way things are going into
society is to build networks
with uh a lot of talented people the
young talented ambitious people
with um a particular way of looking at
the world and so what we're trying to do
is build a network around our project of
people who are interested in
really dissecting these political
problems that we're faced with
and these social problems and and coming
up with productive
answers to them not necessarily in the
short term like policy and so on but in
the longer term vision
and understanding so and and our
expectation and our hope
is that by building this community we
will help positively contribute to
um our our
society's development over the last
couple or sorry the the next couple
decades where i think
such people will hopefully will be at a
high premium and hopefully we'll be able
to provide some of that
so that's the overall pitch for the
project um and that'll give you a
background for
why we do what we do which is again as
peter was saying
long form publishing analysis vision
that kind of stuff so i'll turn it over
to ash to fill in some of the stuff
we've done
yeah thanks wolf so you know as wolf was
like
laid out very well there we're
interested in
looking at things not from an sort of
abstract perspective
or you could even say from an objective
perspective
because when you're looking at the sorts
of stories we're covering
alternative governance models or
development or power elites thinking
about something or
why have institutional failures occurred
these are not stories
that you can just kind of look at from a
bird's eye view as if you're not part of
the story that's going on
um one of the things that we in
particular did early on that helped
bootstrap the publication
was on the ground coverage we had
an excellent piece done very early on in
the project about xinjiang
uh and the camps for uyghurs and the
situation in the
uh cities in that region there uh we had
people report to us about the yellow
vest protest in france
about the protest in chile um kazakhstan
and some of the interesting stuff going
on there basically in all these cases
we're trying to identify who are the
institution builders
and who are the i know samuel comes on
this thing a lot so let's see the live
players
uh involved in these stories and
you know on the one hand uh
there is an event that goes on in the
world right now we have a pandemic
um it has been the event maybe now it's
becoming the setting for other events
protests mass evictions and so on and so
forth
but uh within that setting there are
people who are responsible
to some degree for things going on in
the world you know
i've looked at pieces that have just
talked about
institutional failure in a very abstract
sense
we're not interested in that kind of
analysis
we want to know who did or did fail to
make a decision
uh who built the institution when it was
working why is it no longer working
so that's like the lens through which we
kind of view
all of the things we cover uh the china
bead card events and so on
um we have as i'm sure a lot of you know
more recently moved into doing salons as
well
um and there we try to talk to some of
the most interesting people
um who are actually building
institutions or projects
doing insightful analysis today so we've
had vitalik buterin on
uh john tallinn uh michael lind recently
who's the best-selling author has
interesting work on
the new class for and class analysis uh
so covering a range of topics here
basically we're interested
in people who are actually trying to
figure out how the world works
and are putting skin in the game right
uh either providing analysis
or building something uh ideally
that is based on the assumption that
their analysis is correct
because you know this is in a way uh how
you know you could trust someone
um overall uh
our coalescing together
let's say of narrative long-form and
analysis seems to have gone over
pretty well it's i i think something
that's getting people who
either thought of politics as something
that doesn't impact them
i think especially in the tech sector
there's this kind of assumption that you
can just escape
you know decentralize or or build some
kind of a blockchain
and then you can ignore the hard work of
politics or
institution building um i you know i i
think this
illusion is ever more starting to fade
uh
and being based in san francisco as a
project uh i think
that you know i proud to say a lot of
the work we've done has helped
add to that i just want to add to
something peter said though so i'm based
in toronto
um perhaps there's other people here
also based in the city
and as i'm here i'm starting to see
interesting convergences between these
cities
toronto has a lot of um ties
in a way to the bay area people don't
know this but a lot of
the original research on deep learning
on ai and other issues
occurred in this city and i've
seen ever more institutional ties
growing between these two cities
it's made me interested in thinking
about where else in america what other
cities are starting to learn from the
bay area
maybe in ways that are imperceptible uh
palladium's lens does come out of the
bay area subculture in a way
right we're trying not to just fill up
some pre-established
position on the political spectrum we're
interested in substance
um but
given that the bay area seems to be
having cultural impact
in other cities this gives me some hope
that the kind of analysis palladium is
doing
will also start increasingly to
capture the imaginations of people who
are trying to actually
uh do something useful or understand the
world better
outside of one ecosystem so this is a
project that
you know we're looking at uh
at north america as a whole really um
that's maybe just some sketching around
uh the
finer details of what we're doing and
why we're doing it
um i know that we kind of wanted to
touch on a couple issues that are of
most
relevance or interest to us at the
moment uh wolf
you want to know some stuff about
american
elite education and culture so yeah
again
yeah cool thanks ash um
one way to follow on what ash was just
saying about
kind of the west coast and kind of the
the cultural project
uh in a way of of sort of the bay area
extended culture and the cultural
project of palladium
and connect that to the elite formation
issue is
uh we think it's it's
yeah we think there's actually something
important happening
on the west coast in terms of like
ability to think about
uh think in new ways and think new
things
that isn't just in the established
institutional paradigms
and so one of the big issues that we
focus on domestically
in america is how does the elite think
how do they think about themselves
um how do they educate themselves
how basically how are we running this
country
right or or this this continent really i
mean we're talking to some canadians
here as well
half of us are canadian um but
there's so so this is one of the big
central issues that we've been really
interested in what i think our most
sort of popular and well-known article
in this vein was
natalia deshawn's article the real
problem at yale is not free speech where
she was looking at the
uh the kind of culture of elites
of elite self-conception at elite
universities right now
and how a lot of people are presenting
themselves as
kind of less privileged than they
actually are
as a way partially to get in on the
whole
um privileged politics
thing but also because there's no
positive
narrative there's no positive
self-conception of an elite as such
right now and that's that's sort of one
of the big problems that we want to look
at is like okay there's no
you you need an elite in society you
always have an elite there's always some
relatively smaller group of people who
holds the preponderance of power
and how those people think and operate
is
is of supreme importance and if they
don't have
a positive self-conception of what
they're doing then
you have a very serious situation in
your society and i think that's the
situation we're in right now so this is
one of the dimensions along which
we we sort of orient our work we we're
looking at this question of
what should a responsible elite look
like and what does it actually look like
in america and so we've got some more
stuff coming out
um on america's elite schools
uh besides natalia's article which was
great
we that's that's obviously one of the
huge central
central kind of happening points uh
where where this stuff takes shape
and we are
[Music]
you know in in the through a thread
through the whole project is this
concept of like
what does a responsibility look like
what is an elite that takes itself
seriously as an elite
and thinks of itself in a positive way
and is actually able to deliver on that
what does that actually look like um so
this is
you know we've looked at governance in
many countries around the world
through that lens of like well how
should we be thinking of an elite and
we've looked at
in america the particular pathologies we
have right now
um with you know lack of responsibility
and the coronavirus crisis how no one
has been able to kind of like
again take that mantle of responsibility
how
um you know what what
creates the competent institutions that
america does have we just had an article
come out on
on why the technology sector
tends to be more competent than let's
say the traditional government
um in terms of like what kind of
formation environment they have how
they're thinking about the thing
so there's a bunch of these aspects that
we're looking at that's kind of like our
domestic
our major domestic project is what
should the american league
elite be thinking like and how are they
currently
thinking and i'll leave it at that i i
think that's one of the most important
issues that we're faced with but
obviously it's not everything
ash go for go add your part to this
yeah you know so
kind of touching off the global
counterpart of what wolf was just
talking about
um one of the main focuses
of palladium from the start has been
this idea that we're living in a time
when governance model there is no longer
a monopoly on models of governance
uh you know i personally this has always
been a fascinating thing
for me i studied uh economics in my
undergrad years
and at that time i had written a paper
um i must have been about 18 or 19 at
the time on
uh the chinese party states
constitutional model
and i remember at the time one of the
things that fascinated me about this was
i was shocked at the level of
thinking that the chinese state was
doing
in terms of building a model of
governance that was sovereign
to and in competition with the american
model
now this was obviously couched in
certain ways they're interested in
win-win cooperation or in
you know peaceful development but there
was an immense amount of thought
put into the idea that what china was
building was a uniquely chinese path of
development
um since then i think that
understanding has crept out into the
discourse in a way
bigger way but quite late in a way right
because we're at a point now where
the relationship between china and the
us is something like a second cold war
or at the very least a contest for
control
over the global economy over
institutions
why is this the case i would posit that
since the cold war
ended there was an assumption that if
you wanted to
participate in economic prosperity and
stability
there was one way to do it uh you buy
into the american alliance and the
american model of governance
more or less if you do this you will
have those things
there are some exceptions to this
obviously saudi arabia has never
implemented american social values
uh singapore has economic prosperity
and english linguistic familiarity
but it has always framed itself as
having asian values
um you know in practice this means maybe
a more authoritarian
form of government although one that is
still somewhat democratic
uh and harsher enforcement of social
norms
but generally speaking it was understood
that these were kind of
you know iterations or maybe
unprincipled exceptions
of the american model
this is no longer the case and i would
basically say here that
the fatal mistake that was made was
thinking that we did not have to pay
attention
to what elites in rising states and
powers were thinking
had we looked at what the chinese elite
was saying
to itself and taken it seriously we
would have predicted their development
path
ex you know with extreme accuracy what
we're doing at palladium
is taking them seriously better late
than never right
uh and i think that what we're seeing is
that there are things that we can learn
from this model in terms of challenging
our assumptions of what is necessary for
stability and for prosperity and so
on uh american america obviously is a
very different country
we have different expectations and
social morays
but i think that four american elites
american governors to have more humility
about their expectations and assumptions
will be a good thing we've done
translation work
you know we've done deeper dives or you
know
writers verbally moved on deeper dives
as to what
discourse is like among chinese
political elites
we've brought that as well uh i've
mentioned already we've looked at
kazakhstan
we've looked at eastern europe we're
soon going to be having a piece on
russia
and its project of using history to
solidify
its national identity uh
basically in a world that's gonna become
more multi-polar
we're gonna have to become conversant
not just with the ways that our elites
think
but with the ways that elites in a
number of other powers think
and that's one of our central goals in
terms of global coverage
there's a lot of other stuff i could
discuss here peter but i think i'll
maybe leave it to you and we could pivot
to q a here
yeah that's some good stuff um so if you
have any questions start dropping in the
chat box now and i'll call on you
uh please unmute yourself um so i'll
have some questions to warm up the room
uh one one of them is a broad one um
what sort
of individuals uh institutions or
countries that you think are exceptional
institutional
institution builders or what samuel
calls live players
yeah what ones that you think are um
worthy of investigating or worthy that
we should put on
on our radar well if you want to take
the american side
i mean i i can kind of it's hard to say
yeah go for it yeah i'll get it started
here
one of our first salons here was with uh
robert zubrin
who is a big advocate of a direct mars
mission and you know a central focus
that
he has is why has the uh space program
that america built
failed um when america was
building you know set itself to school
in the early 60s they're gonna put a man
on the moon
this was not feasible this was not
politically feasible it had no popular
support it was not technologically
possible
and by the end of the decade they did it
that
process of institution building you know
it included people like
uh von braun you know a number of people
who built
um engineering institutions
scientific institutions but also
political institutions
um you know something that i i mentioned
earlier but we'll bring it again
there's this assumption today that there
is science and technology on the one
hand and politics on the other
uh in the post-war period when we look
at the institutions that were built this
also applies to things like darpa
um this applies to the research done in
the
u.s military that resulted in things
like our gps systems
uh or on technologies like cpus that
appear on
you know in a lot of our electronic
devices those institutions
were built politically by people who
understood political landscape
and had goals that required scientific
and technological
means to be realized i do think that
political impetus is often the first
thing to occur in these institutions
and then a lot of the things that we
assume are just this kind of
tide of uh technological progress are
often downstream
and obviously they can develop in ways
that their founders didn't foresee
but they are the result of you know
they're not just the result of some
inevitability of history
so i'll uh it'll be my answer for this
one
wolf did you want to jump in here as
well or shall we i mean maybe i'll get
more specific about like particular
projects that i find interesting
i mean so obvious ones the big the big
kind of
institution founders that everyone's
aware of who are actually building
things
um you know the big silicon valley
companies
in particular um
i don't know if these really count but
amazon and spacex
uh not not actually based in the bay
area but uh
i think those ones are good examples of
of kind of like people who are actively
founding institutions
and and building these
new pieces of machinery i'm not sure
there's that much
else going on it's like
you know overseas there's a lot going on
you look at
what g is doing with the chinese
communist party
um uh one of our sort of like big
surprise stories was
what's been going on in kazakhstan where
nurse ultan has actually just been
totally rebuilding that country um
in a quite optimistic way and
and then we you know we've we've been
starting to look
briefly at the the situation in russia
recently
like uh putin is obviously one of these
people who's been actually building
things
in america i think we've had kind of a
long period
of no one having the power
or vision to build that much so it's
hard to really name
i i'm sure there's many good examples
it's just off the top of my head it's
hard to name
a lot of exciting stuff other than uh
some of these companies that have been
founded in the last 20 years yeah well
and but i think that that
is um a part of that is
because the system of public
institutions right formal government
institutions
have decayed in a big way the instant
the public institutional golden age
in america i think was the post-war era
up until essentially the 60s you know
the space program that i mentioned
earlier
wasn't the first great institution that
was built this kind of public
institution it was one of the last
from the 70s onward we see decay but we
see also
spillover effects from those
institutions
in terms of public education in terms of
technologies
that now allow a bunch of private
institutions that are highly competent
to be built
the key point i'm trying to make here is
that when we talk about institutions
this can apply to companies it can apply
to
states maybe it can apply to religious
cults
uh we're using this term in a broad way
the claim we're making here is that
there are equivalencies
between good well-run states and
well-run companies and well-run cults
and their failure modes are often
similar too
when as in america's case may be the
system of institutions becomes so
spread thin that uh it's really
impossible to make a decision
so that the institution as a whole can
function right
what what american decision maker has
the power to really say
we need a systemic change right uh
there is really no one in control of the
whole thing
so likewise when
we've seen this in a number of private
companies maybe apple is on this path
when the people who know how the
institution is meant to run
are no longer in the picture and the
succession is not achieved
then those institutions will decline and
so
a lot of our analysis on uh
both how institutions are founded and
how they decline will be the same across
states companies and so on
excellent okay uh let's get to some of
these questions yeah we've got some
really good questions um so susan you're
going to meet yourself
[Music]
where's susan
susie no let me i'm gonna unmute you
susan
yeah there you go yes yes um hello
um so yeah that's great um i love what
you guys are doing
um so what uh when you
when you achieve the goal that you're
working on in terms of
understanding how the elite think what
what is
you know what what is that information
going to do for you
as far as you know leading to
redesigning a new system
so um yeah good question
i'm i wouldn't characterize it quite as
narrowly as like characterizing how the
elite thinks i think
um that's kind of one of the smaller
aspects it's it's more like um
the larger trajectory of how they have
thought in the past versus thinking now
and how and like
what things could look like differently
and and really focusing on the
institutional part
uh as for like how they think now i mean
i think dan feldman in the chat actually
character
caricatures it pretty well which is like
they the the driving ethos in america
right now especially among the elite is
like
let's just
let's just make sure that we can get our
own kids into the right schools
and you know make sure do whatever we
have to do
to the country or whatever to like make
sure that you know i'm getting my comfy
retirement
this is you know obviously a caricature
but also it's it's an ethos that's
that's
quite widespread among the elite in the
sense that like
it's not an ethos of i'm in charge of
this situation
and i'm responsible for the situation
but rather just like
i'm i'm just some upper middle class
person
i just want to get my kids into the
right school right and i oh i happen to
have a lot of power so i'm going to like
use that power
to keep stability keep the system
running
and make sure that i'm getting mine
and that that is sort of like
uh the current situation or like a lot
of the the
trouble with the current situation i
would diagnose that as
in a way a lack
either a lack of ambition or lack of
coordination if if
you had the well there's many different
ways
of of sort of describing what exactly is
wrong with that i think
one of the mistakes that a lot of people
make though is they think oh the elite
should be
less selfish they should be like
you know more altruistic care about
everyone else uh
they should not just be
they should give away their power or
something like this and i think
that doesn't actually solve the problem
or and is like
some combination of that and it's it's
completely unrealistic i think
the way that i see this getting solved
is again you need someone in charge who
has the power
who understands that they have the power
and has big enough goals of what to do
with that power
um you know obviously you want
benevolent goals and so on but at least
big enough goals that they see
their imperative as being something more
than just maintaining their own personal
fiefdom
um and i think we see this in the past
where you had times
uh you know obviously in a war situation
they're going to see
they're going to have a very large goal
which is which is survival and conquest
um in the post-war scenario you know
people
had big goals like let's go to the moon
or let's prove that we're better than
the soviets
or whatever um
and i think i think it's necessary to
have like those big driving goals
that for which you can't just suppress
the rest of society you have to mobilize
the rest of society
around some grander conception of why we
even have a society like
that that's perhaps one of the most
important questions what is society for
right it's something that someone built
it's built for purpose
to maintain it is an ongoing process of
construction
why are we doing it right is it pure
altruism no one does
like very few people do that much for
pure altruism they have some motive what
are they trying to do with it um
and what's exciting about about the fact
that we have a society as opposed to not
having a society
why should i maintain it why should i
add to it why should i grow it
um and and i think that has to come
along with society-sized goals you need
to have some conception of
where are we going as a society what
kind of society we're building
something that isn't just some nice
story that we tell people but it's
something we actually believe
and that's so i think that's like one of
the critical aspects
um i'm not sure if this is really
answering your question but
it's that's sort of one of the critical
aspects in how i'm seeing
the the problem of
elite motivation i guess and then
the there's the whole other side which
is
do they have do the elites have the
institutional coherence
and the knowledge to actually coordinate
around such a goal
and achieve it and actually go and build
the structures of society
that um that would allow them to do
anything
so yeah i'd like to jump in here quickly
before i think there's a good
uh illustration that we can make here
with um
so this will be kind of a sneak peek for
the stoa uh
but someone in the palladium community
is writing a piece on her experience at
harvard
uh and one of the most fascinating
discussion topics is the way that career
fairs work
and there's a very interesting thing
that happens because the harvard
community right we
you know there's children of
billionaires there's uh
people from you know from wealthy
families in other countries
one would expect right any one of us who
hasn't thought about
oh if only i'd been born with a billion
dollars or
10 million dollars to my name what would
i do with it
so you would expect it at a place where
a lot of people come
from you know families of means that
there would be a big focus on okay
you have access to these kinds of forms
of dynastic wealth
how do you use them well how do you
achieve great things with them how do
you take
maybe a minor elite dynasty and make it
into a great one
this doesn't happen at all what happens
instead is that these kids are
shuttled off to career fairs where
mckinsey
and a few banks and maybe 10 or 20 other
companies
are at every single affair for every
single faculty via the sciences or arts
or business
or whatever um the result is that
there is immense pressure and
competition there is a sort of striver
mentality created
the impression is that there are very
few jobs that will
allow their applicants to both earn a
good living
and keep their status you know the sort
of job that a harvard graduate should
have
i think that this is basically a
terrible situation to be in
because if we live in a society where a
lot of our institutions were
founded by very publicly oriented uh
decision makers whose and those
institutions depend on
that you know the people running them
think in long-term ways
and think in ways that how do you invest
in an institution or how do you
make the sacrifices necessary to keep it
running
uh that could be an education system it
could be scientific research it could be
international alliances and personal
diplomatic relationships
you know there are a lot of these kind
of miniature empires that exist
when most of the elite class inculcates
itself into the mindset that the thing
that i should be striving for is a job
at mckinsey
i don't think that those institutions
will end up lasting and we've seen this
the short-termism
across both the private and the public
sector yeah so this
i think that's a good illustration there
i i have something to add to this so i
there's an underlying assumption that
we're making here which is
uh a substantial social constructivism
of goals um that that basically
even the elite is very much
influenced by what the narrative is
about what their role in society is and
what they're supposed to be doing
and right now the narrative is that
you're supposed to be
upper middle class that all elites are
bad you're not supposed to be an elite
you're supposed to get rid of your power
except
only publicly really uh and and just be
upper middle class
and and go and get your like slick
consulting job at mckinsey fit into the
system
you know make your 200 000 a year maybe
your 600 000
a year and you know just make sure that
no one
no one rocks your boat too much and
that's kind of
like that's how things are narrativized
right now of like what you're supposed
to be doing
and if that is the narrative that we
have
floating around that's available that's
what people are going to do
um so one of the things that i want to
do with this project and and
you know i hope other people contribute
to this is i think we need to build up
a narrative of what is a positive role
for an elite in society that isn't
just something lame like that but is
saying no you have power
you're supposed to build that power
you're supposed to build a large
uh a powerful system of governance and
then go
and do these these you know ambitious
things uh in society with it like
let's actually solve our social problems
like we're supposed to actually build
institutions and solve our social
problems
and yes that involves large amounts of
personal power large amounts of power
concentration at the top
and and a particular ethos a particular
way of being
someone mentioned no bless oblige in the
trap very much that kind of thing but we
also have to
i think recognize
where that comes from what it goes along
with i think
people are often trying to come up with
these narratives where
being in a being an elite is sort of
purely a position of liability you're
supposed to just help everyone else for
for no particular reason to yourself
you're supposed to be altruistic you're
supposed to be a public servant
i think these narratives actually are
not inspiring
they fail to capture the reality of
what's going on
and so they end up falling out of favor
i think we need narratives that are more
like why do we
help everyone else in society because it
makes us more powerful
right um we help other people because it
makes us
strong i mean it builds a stronger
society that can do more and do more
interesting
things and is more to the glory of its
rulers um
and and so you i think building
alternate narratives from the sort of
like upper middle class
strive within existing institutional
structure to kind of like maintain your
privilege
narrative is is necessary we need
something that's much bolder than that
and i think ironically like everyone
sees the problems with the current like
maintain your privilege model of
eliteness and they move in the
wrong direction from that or for for
good reason it's like oh
why are we supporting an elite that that
is just kind of
um oriented towards perpetuating their
own privilege
for no particular reason uh and they
move like oh well let's just get rid of
that
let's let's share it let's spread it
around whereas i think what has to
happen
is more like let's give that thing a
positive uh
utilization and come up with a positive
narrative of
of the existence of an elite anyway so
this is this is
one of my uh
larger kind of goals with with i think
what we
all need to be working on cool let's
move to more questions though
so jeremy you had a question
you can unmute yourself
yes thanks um yeah i just wondered about
the role of strategic competition with
rival powers and um
in creating competent institutions
historically
do you think that that's a necessary
precondition
and um yeah i just kind of wanted to
hear your thoughts on that
yeah i can jump onto this one go for it
um
i think that strategic competition
usually does end up
forcing these kinds of institutions to
improve yes
so um i'll continue using the space race
example just because i think it's a very
effective
and familiar one but the the space race
you know i think today we have this
narrative that
the apollo program and all of this
occurred because
uh we understood that going to space was
the next chapter of the human story
uh and this kind of thing this is not
the case the soviet union
achieved most of the first milestones in
the space race
america and not all of america but
certain uh
people within its institutions realized
that
you know allowing the soviet union to
achieve dominance in space was a
terrible idea
when the apollo program was being set up
uh
even the scientific community mostly
thought it was a waste of time
uh it did not have a lot of support
there are a lot of other projects going
on right
nuclear energy and nuclear weapons
um you know biology lots of other
projects that could use public patronage
so why should this one get it
uh what happened was that
the pressure placed on u.s elites
and then the skin in the game put in by
kennedy actually publicly saying
that they were going to achieve this uh
you know so
they now it would be more damaging for
them to lose face on the global stage
against the soviet union uh i think that
pressure definitely
um added to the investments
that they were willing to make
institutionally and to how long term
they were thinking
if you are looking at
you know the the survival and global
dominance of your country over the next
50 years over the next 100 years
you're going to be thinking on a level
that you just won't be if
you know you the next election cycle or
the next business cycle
is uh the main you know kpi basically
that you achieve
that you measure success on so i i do
think that that kind of
um competition does create better elites
there's an interesting question here
though as to you know there are
challenges in the world that are not
human opponents
um you know we can think of the climate
we can think of the current pandemic
even
uh it's interesting to me how quickly
the current pandemic moved from being
this biological threat
to a blame game of which powers
or which you know the failures of which
countries
most contributed to the the shutdown and
everything that is coming after
there seems to be this weird tick that
a human opponent causes people
to act in a much more substantive way
than a a more abstract or maybe a
non-visible one does
i think this is generally not a good
situation to be in
because it sort of dooms us to a certain
amount of
uh zero-sum thinking when it comes to
what the future of the whole world looks
like
the future of the species i would like
to figure out ways that maybe we can
have that kind of competition you know
people who talk about um getting off
earth so
wolf you mentioned spacex earlier as an
institution that is
very interesting and obviously its
founder has this very deep commitment
that
the existential risk we face by only
living on one planet
is like such a terrible thing that we
have to figure out a way to get off this
rock
so there are people who can
be motivated in those ways i would like
to know
did ash just uh is his wi-fi
yeah i think so i can get it from there
yeah sure i can pick it up from there
i'm not going to follow exactly the same
thread i have another
related answer to this question which is
that i think there's two things that are
necessary
um to i don't know renew
the institutional structure or the elite
of a country there's one of the things
is you need existential narratives uh
that's my generalization
of the idea of needing like an external
opponent or something
so an existential narrative is something
like you absolutely have to
uh or you feel that you absolutely have
to kind of
pursue this imperative um and
it's a narrative when everyone is kind
of synced up on it
and when you have everyone synced up on
an existential narrative
what you have is a situation
where things that serve the existential
narrative or
or respond to the existential narrative
effectively are easily promoted and
things
that are obviously against serving the
existential narrative are
are easily removed um the politics
becomes a lot easier
of of basically responding to the
existential narrative if everyone is
synced up on it
so i think times of war when some other
country is actually materially about to
like
kill everybody or or wipe you out or you
know completely knock you off your
position
those are very easy scenarios in which
to construct an existential narrative
um but i want to generalize it because
as ash was saying we don't want to just
get into this like zero sum oh yeah we
need to be fighting forever
kind of mood it's it's like the question
is the construction of an existential
narrative and
obviously war is is a very uh common
existential narrative but there are
other ones
you mentioned global warming etc you
mentioned space travel
um you know we could talk about
you could imagine sinking humanity up on
some kind of spiritual existential
narrative or something about
you know people that we've we've our
society has tried
over the last let's say 70 years to sync
people up on kind of like
alleviation of poverty on the question
of like basic human dignity and so on
have tried to make these things sort of
like the central narratives that
that are motivating people um and to
create an existential narrative
in the absence of some
external factor that creates it for you
like war you need
pretty good narrative shaping
institutions
um that are able to kind of convince
everyone
that x is the thing and
um that's i think one of the things that
has been breaking down as we've seen
like
you know the proliferation of many
voices all kind of fighting with each
other
um with with just the general evolution
of our political situation especially
with the internet
uh it's it's not easy to kind of
coordinate everyone around
around any particular large existential
narrative
and also i think there's been kind of a
lack of creativity and a lack of
um vision in in coming up with
with narratives that could actually sync
everyone up um so that's the first part
the second part is obviously you need
the
some baseline level of of institutional
quality and elite quality that's able to
take kind of uh take that narrative and
and do something useful with it
um you know it's not always the case
that every country faced with an actual
existential situation
responds to it appropriately um even if
they're aware of it you know people do
lose wars
uh often due to incompetence and
you know i think i think america was
faced with a pretty clear existential
narrative with with
uh the whole coronavirus situation and
we failed that one
um because of our
our internal incoherence so those are
the two things that i would say go into
that and
that's like my generalization of the
external competition creates competence
uh observation yeah i just want to
clarify the point you're making at the
end there right
uh in a lot of the best analysis that
i've seen
including stuff we've published at
palladium on where the failure was
it was not in preparedness materially
and even institutionally speaking
america was fully prepared for a
pandemic what occurred was a failure of
judgment
where decisions were outsourced to other
institutions
or they were not made or there was no
coordination
between the people with the authority to
make them that was the failure
yeah and or just like you know you
notice
when something comes down the pipe like
kovid there are people who are
actively and and vigorously trying to
respond to that and people who are
not and what needs to happen to to bring
in that renewal is you need to
put those take those actively vigorously
responding people
and and promote them right they need to
move up the chain they need to get into
getting control of more of the
institutional machinery and
that was something that did not happen
most of the people who were actively
vigorously responding to the thing were
more or less locked out of existing
institutional
structure and no one was willing to
promote them or or able to promote them
um and you saw a little bit of it within
existing institutions but
but there wasn't a lot of like large
changes in institutional position on the
basis of who was responding effectively
to the thing and that's uh part of why
we didn't respond to it very well but i
think we can move on to the next
question we've hit that one pretty
thoroughly
cool cool and we're not asking all the
questions in order and we're not going
to get to everyone and i think we have
time just for one more uh we have about
10 more minutes here
um albert lee or albert kim you had a
question
you can unmute yourself
okay how you guys doing um i just
described to your podcast i'm gonna
check out your website i'm really
interested in your stuff
um i think it's like i'm really
interested in what you're about about
you know like the future of governance
and all that
um but what i find really curious is
your emphasis
on the elites um because my question was
uh
what in your analysis uh leads you to
conclude that
there should be a perpetuation of an
elite class rather than
a more focus on decentralized power
sharing
and yeah i know you specifically
mentioned oh the blockchain
you know in san francisco you're like oh
that's not going to happen like
i was i was really curious why you uh
like why you two
went that way because i mean the way i
see it especially
the way things are going like it seems
to me almost like a near-term solution
with society becoming more complex and
like we're involved you know it's like
it's like dancing landscape and like i
don't believe a small group a small
cadre of elites is
going to be able to handle this stuff
and that if we keep abiding by that
model
then where the society is going to
collapse we're going to have to go to
like an industrial age society or
whatnot or even worse
so i just wonder one of your analysis
i'll let you to conclude that
focus on elites which is important into
the future
yes i i can answer that um so the axiom
that i always bring in here is that
power exists
if you always have the ability to
influence other people and to influence
social defense
in society there's there's always this
this power there's there's
ability to gain leverage and the ability
to gain leverage
means that someone is going to have it
someone is going to use it
and they're generally going to use it to
gain more leverage
because political leverage social
leverage
allows them to um
you know influence events in the way
that they want them to go
so power is useful right so people are
going to seek power
and the result of this is that
there's going to be competition for
power and there's going to be someone
there's going to be people attempting to
concentrate power and the thing about
power is that
once you have it concentrated you can
prevent other people
from getting it and that means that you
tend to get relatively stable
concentrations of power it's you don't
generally get a balance
um of powers except where the powers are
heterogeneous in type
in which case usually the thing that
gets worked out is some kind of alliance
cooperation deal between the
heterogeneous powers
such that they become a unified power
and so this is the genesis of an elite
and a genesis of like
all kind of centralized power going back
to the advent of
of the cell right the individual
biological cell which is
a region of controlled resources
surrounded by a wall um
there's this is like the fundamental
fact of life is power
and with technological progress
over the last you know three billion
years but especially the last 300 years
we have increasing sophistication
of our means of power it's increasing
sophistication of ability
to coordinate more and more resources
and to apply
force further and further various kinds
of force not just physical
um and so i think the
this analysis has sort of like nothing
to do with what we want it has nothing
to do with
with even how humans are this is
relatively fundamental facts about
how influence over things happening in
the universe
works and uh the conclusion that i draw
from all of this
is that with increasing technological
sophistication you always get
on average in the long term more
concentration of power more
centralization of power
and larger empires so
i think that that is generally the story
of history that's generally what we're
seeing
and so then if we apply that to our
current situation it's like
okay increasing technological
sophistication we are likely to continue
having an elite
it is likely therefore to continue being
very important
what this elite wants to do what they're
trying to do how they're doing it etc
and there's this this huge important
problem of okay we have
power how shall we use it i want to
approach this question as well for maybe
the different direction
um you know you're mentioning blockchain
i think
probably in the last 20 years the
biggest thing we thought was going to
cause this kind of
radical decentralization was the
internet um
digital technologies in particular what
do they do they operate in scale
they build networks they make those
networks legible to each other
but especially to the central
coordinating power
usually the company and uh increasingly
in the last 10 years they have gathered
they've harvested we could say data from
that user base
um governments were being out-competed
for some time
in their ability to control those kinds
of technologies
that's no longer the case um we saw with
covet that especially east asian states
had you know on on a very to a
significant degree outcompeted the us
government
but even in the u.s we had um a coveted
open database uh you know we're seeing
in the uk as well
almost every country with the state
capacity
to enter uh the realm of digital
technology has begun to exercise its
power
in a digital way and so i think that
with technology
you know and who knows i mean maybe we
get
some technological advance at some point
that blocks this trend somehow
um but historically what we have seen
is that almost every technological
advance uh
has been a way ultimately for
governing institutions to have increased
legibility over
populations that they govern now you can
have very dystopian versions of this
right if you're if you're in xinjiang
you're getting like a very
you know hard-fisted and fairly ruthless
application of this
but you can also have more um
you know peaceable and let's say
pro-social version so
in taiwan uh this is something i wrote
about for the magazine
taiwan had an a very
open and data-heavy approach you know
using mechanisms we would not want to
use in the us
on a popular level like combining
insurance data
with travel data tracking people's
movements and so on
but because taiwan has built
institutions that
increase the ability for citizens in the
country
to inform the policies and decisions of
the central power
there's much more of a dynamic
relationship between center and
periphery
so i'm not proposing that there's some
single model but
across all these models the key thing
that matters is whether the
institutionals are functional and
responsive
and the thing i would basically say here
is that an institution
by its nature has a group of owners or
at least managers
that understand how it works and that
have privileged information
as to that institution and i i have not
seen any good argument that
a technological solution uh is going to
route around that fundamental fact
i i would uh want to add one more thing
in response to
dan feldman's question or comment that
um you know technology accelerates the
constitution concentration of power
um does that concentration become so
great
that the larger system destabilizes and
how will nature resolve
accelerating technology uh further
coalescing power i think this is a
really important and deep question
um the answer is that yes concentrations
and centralizations of power are fragile
they they grow they take over the space
but then because they are optimized for
dominance and not
for sustainability they inevitably
are mortal and start to decay
and they they don't contain within them
the systems of their own
uh renewal of neces of governing the
governing the sort of sort of whole
cybernetic stack uh towards like the
elimination of cancers and parasites
um and so
you end up with with death basically you
end up with mortality
of these large complex systems and so
the
key the key thing there
is that as we build these large complex
systems of
our society um we want to
pay a lot more attention to that
sustainability question
as we you know we build a new order um
or or if we're ever in the position of
building a new order you want to pay a
lot of attention to that sustainability
question which is the long-term uh
governance of the internal order making
sure that it's not just
immediately collapsing and then through
these collapses or when we're
anticipating a collapse
we want to pay a lot of attention to um
the survivability of that collapse and
making sure again
that we are sowing those seeds of new
growth in at that
that sort of height of of power so
again this is how animals and plants
solve this problem animals and plants
have the problem
that a concentration of order is
inherently fragile and mortal
they always die which means they need to
pay some attention to
okay well how do i then redirect some
fraction of my resources to
perpetuation of of uh
the form through reproduction and i
think we have to think that way about
society as well
uh and this is partially the frame that
palladium comes in with is if we're
facing the death of a number of
our institutions that have been going
for a while they had an established
order
but they've been building up too much
entropy um
we're going to face the death of those
things we need to be thinking about
seeds of new growth
we need to be founding the new
institutions the new ways of thinking
the new networks that are going to be
building
the next phase of order and i think
these are really
fundamental issues in in how order and
power works
in in the universe and so i think we do
have to keep those in mind when thinking
about
where we are in that sort of cycle of
mortality
uh and and what is the appropriate
response to that and so i think
uh what we need to be thinking now is
how do we sow the the seeds of new
growth
uh what exactly do we need to be
building in terms of institutions and
ideas
and then as we plan for uh
a subsequent order to be uh to be
rebuilt
um let's think about that sustainability
question as well
making sure that we have all the like
cybernetic um
regulatory mechanisms that keep it from
immediately collapsing
let me just make a final point here as
well uh
i don't think what either of us are
claiming is that elites kind of
never have over and that there is kind
of one permanent elite that has ruled
all through history or anything like
this this is not the case uh
elites do in a lot of cases have more
staying power than we realize
so one of my favorite examples here is
florence where
uh if you look at the most prominent
family of thorns today
a number of them were also among the
prominent families of the 1400s
that is an incredible endurance
you know think about all the stages of
history from
you know 30 years war to the industrial
revolution to multiple world wars that
you had to survive
while maintaining your position however
you obviously also have turnover
but that turnover often occurs by
kind of maybe a lower rank of an elite
overthrowing an upper rank
even in china today after the communist
and cultural revolutions
a lot of the red princelings as they
call them have
roots in the landowner class of the
country during the end of the imperial
era
i'd also i know elite overproduction has
been mentioned a few times in the chat
um i think that what elite
overproduction often
is is a dead institution that has
maintained itself
as a status granting mechanism so what i
mean by that is you know
if if oxford tomorrow morning stop doing
any useful research or harvard tomorrow
morning
stop doing any useful research how long
would it take
for people to stop going well i wasn't
going to say it but how long would it
take for people to stop going to harvard
it wouldn't happen tomorrow morning
so you know law schools or non-profits
and this kind of thing
or the u.n maybe you know these
things can retain status long after they
lose
the ability to generate value
and notice that even when those things
die an elite that jettisons 70 or 80
of its members but 20 keep their place
is it's still you know a lot of those
same people and i think in reality what
usually happens in turnover is
some portion of the governing class
maintains its position
some new proportion of institution
builders or
you know new men as they're called
sometimes in the classical histories
come in and some proportion is medicined
but there is a continuity in the sense
that
i think there is often more turnover
even in these radical
uh disruptions than we usually think is
the case
um yeah with with that i'm seeing a lot
of
great comments but peter are we are we
out of time
yeah so uh we can close the official
recording portion now
and then if you guys want to stay i can
take the grounds yeah
one final thing i would add is i've i've
loved this conversation
and i see a lot of familiar faces that
i'd love to have more involved in
in our end of the conversation over at
palladium so please do
subscribe to palladium become a
subscriber become a member
um and come participate in our in our
conversations in our salons
and um in our community
yeah looking forward to chatting with
some of you and that's the way you can
help
if you're interested i definitely
recommend checking out the
their blog and their podcast um so we'll
close out this official portion
uh and then you guys can hang out more
in chat i have to run
but uh in a moment i'll plug some
announcements but wolf
ash thanks so much guys for coming on
i've been waiting for
palladium to have a presence at the
start and i'm glad you finally did and
i'm looking forward for more uh
collaboration definitely
um so upcoming uh events uh
yeah let's see i'll just plug uh two
one is coming up in an hour um maybe
would you like to
meet yourself and kind of let us know
what's going on there
uh yeah sure uh stoned with caves ahead
at the stoa is happening in just a
little under an hour at 8 pm eastern
um kabe was on my series rather
sexuality
doing an interview and afterwards agreed
to
host a session where he plans to get
stoned
and have a conversation with whoever
shows up there's nothing else planned
you're free to show up stoned to if you
live in a place where you are
you know free to partake um
uh but feel free to show up sober as
well uh it'll
surely be very like uh intimate and
honest conversation
uh yeah i have no idea what's going on
let's find out uh and then tomorrow we
have forrest landry the game b
metaphysician uh he's having a session
on human collaboration
that's at 9 30 pm eastern time and then
thursday morning on july 9th at 10
a.m eastern time we have how to win
friends and influence people during a
metacrisis
uh franchise owner of the dale carnegie
training is going to come and then teach
us how to do that
apparently so uh rsvp to the website
and uh we have uh the store is based off
a gift economy if you're inspired to
give a gift to the store
uh you can do so at the store ca slash
gift
all right thanks so much everyone
boom